<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-franke-isis-p2mp" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <!-- The abbreviated title is used in the page header - it is only necessary if the 
         full title is longer than 39 characters -->

    <title abbrev="Point-to-Multipoint for IS-IS">Point-to-Multipoint for IS-IS</title>
    <author fullname="Christian Franke" initials="C."
            surname="Franke">
      <organization>NetDEF</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>
          <!-- Reorder these if your country does things differently -->
          <code></code>
          <city>Leipzig</city>
          <region></region>
          <country>DE</country>
        </postal>

        <email>chris@opensourcerouting.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="David Lamparter" initials="D." surname="Lamparter">
      <organization>NetDEF</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>
          <code>04103</code>
          <city>Leipzig</city>
          <country>Germany</country>
        </postal>
        <email>david@opensourcerouting.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="3" month="July" year="2015" />

    <area>Routing</area>

    <workgroup>Network Working Group</workgroup>
    <keyword>IS-IS Multipoint Multicast</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>
        This document describes a new mode operation for IS-IS. In addition
        to the existing LAN and point-to-point mode of operation, a point-to-multipoint
        mode is defined. This mode is useful for operation both on networks with more than
        two routers where multicast is expensive in comparison to unicast and on
        networks where the common methodology of creating a LAN pseudonode cannot adequately
        reflect metrics.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
      <t>The core functionality of the protocol outlined in this document
        consists of an additional Subnetwork dependent function per <xref
          target="IS-IS">Section 8 of ISO/IEC 10589:2002.</xref>
        In that regard, the next section can be understood as new section "8.5
        Point-to-multipoint networks".</t>
      <t>The outlined protocol is remotely similar to the derelict section
        "8.3 ISO 8208 subnetworks" in that multiple point-to-point adjacencies
        are established on an interface.</t>
      <t>Point-to-multipoint operation of IS-IS is thus not a new idea; in
        fact section 6.2 already mentions "multipoint links."  This document
        re-enables the concept.</t>
    </section>

    <?rfc needLines="5" ?>

    <section anchor="pseudocirc" title="P2MP Pseudocircuits">
      <t>In place of ISO 8473 call management establishing sessions, this
        document establishes pairwise "pseudocircuits" between two IS on a
        common medium.  Multiple such pseudocircuits can normally exist on
        one P2MP interface.</t>
      <t>Each pseudocircuit operates, aside from subnetwork attachment
        procedures, exactly as a PtP link.</t>

      <?rfc needLines="5" ?>

      <section title="Pseudocircuit behaviour">
        <t>An implementation maintains a set of pseudocircuits per P2MP
          interface.  Each pseudocircuit is uniquely identified by the local
          interface and peer's SNPA address.</t>
        <t>Each participating system MUST use a consistent SNPA address per
          local interface.  A change in SNPA address results in all neighbors
          treating the interface as distinct from the previous one.  A system
          MAY support multiple SNPA addresses per interface by treating them as
          distinct interfaces.</t>
        <t>Unnumbered media are not supported by this protocol.  Each
          participant on a link MUST have an unique SNPA address on that
          link.</t>

        <t>As pseudocircuits are dynamic in nature, they must be created and
          destroyed as needed.  Destruction is triggered when no mechanism
          holds the pseudocircuit alive anymore, which means:
          <list>
            <t>PtP adjacency timeout functionality (<xref target="IS-IS">IS-IS
                section 8.2.6</xref>) has moved the pseudocircuit to Down
              state</t>
            <t>The holdtime of any multicast autodiscovery P2MP Hello PDUs has
              expired.</t>
            <t>Manual configuration or lower layer autodiscovery no longer
              lists the neighbor.</t>
          </list>
          Unless all of these conditions are fulfilled, systems MUST NOT
          destroy a pseudocircuits.  The pseudocircuit is instead kept in Down
          state, and further Hellos MUST be sent on the pseudocircuit.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Neighbor IS discovery">
        <t>The discovery machinery provides a set of suggested pseudocircuit
          neighbors per P2MP interface, identified by their SNPA addresses.
          Implementations MUST create a pseudocircuit for each suggested
          neighbor unless directed otherwise by operator configuration.
          Additional information (metrics, etc.) MAY be passed up by the
          discovery mechanism, associated with individual neighbors, but this
          is not core part of the discovery mechanism.</t>
        <t>The list is the union of the result of each of the following
          sources of neighbor information.  The IS implementation SHOULD
          provide user configuration to disable individual mechanisms and/or
          filter neighbors as a security measure.</t>

        <section title="Manual configuration">
          <t>A list of neighbor IS MAY be configured by the user, providing
            possible neighbor's SNPAs on an interface.  Pseudocircuits created
            in such a way are not destroyed unless the operator removes the
            configuration entry.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Lower layer autodiscovery">
          <t>Lower protocol layers (VPLS, IEEE 802.11) may be able to provide
            a list of attached neighbors.  This list MAY be fed into the
            pseudocircuit creation process.  Destruction of pseudocircuits
            does not happen as long as the lower layer suggests the neighbor
            is still present.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Multicast autodiscovery">
          <t>For broadcast capable networks, this document defines an
            autodiscovery mechanism based on multicasting Hello packets.
            This mechanism MAY be disabled by the user, but MUST be
            implemented for all lower layer link types with (limited or full)
            broadcast capability.</t>
          <t>A system MAY implement a receive-only passive multicast
            autodiscovery mode where it forms pseudocircuits on receiving
            P2MP Hello PDUs, but does not send such PDUs itself.</t>
          <t>Multicast autodiscovery P2MP Hello PDUs are distinguished by not
            containing a RFC5303 Three-Way Adjacency TLV.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Inbound hellos">
          <t>Received P2MP Hello PDUs trigger pseudocircuit creation (subject
            to configuration restrictions) in all cases where no matching
            existing pseudocircuit can be found.  This handles both remote
            creation of pseudocircuits as well as incoming multicast
            autodiscovery PDUs.</t>
          <t>Pseudocircuits created from received P2MP Hello PDUs are held
            in Down state (and further Hellos are sent on the pseudocircuit)
            beyond the PtP timeout per <xref target="IS-IS">IS-IS section
              8.2.6</xref> if a multicast autodiscovery PDU was received from
            the neighbor and its holdtime expires later than the PtP
            timeout.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="General considerations">
          <t>It should be noted that while the Multicast autodiscovery
            mechanism requires broadcast capability, no other part of the
            protocol does.  The P2MP interface type can be used on
            non-transitive and/or non-broadcast interfaces.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <?rfc needLines="5" ?>

      <section title="Adjacency formation">
        <t>Since there is no underlying protocol layer
          partitioning the link into actual PtP circuits in this case, additional handling
          is required on bringing up the individual pseudocircuit
          adjacencies.</t>
        <t>To prevent different pseudocircuits from "bleeding" into each other,
          implementations of this protocol MUST enable <xref target="RFC5303"/>
          on all P2MP pseudocircuits, with changes as follows:
          <list>
            <t>Received IIH PDUs on P2MP pseudocircuits without the
              Point-to-Point Three-Way Adjacency option MUST be discarded.  The
              TLV is not optional on pseudocircuit adjacencies but rather
              mandatory.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="processing" title="PDU generation and processing">
      <section title="LSP, CSNP, PSNP and all other non-Hello PDU types">
        <t>All PDU types that are not Hello PDUs, e.g. L1/L2 LSP PDUs, L1/L2
          CSNP/PSNP PDUs, FS-LSP, FS-CSNP and FS-PSNP PDUs are processed on
          P2MP interfaces by dispatching them to individual pseudocircuits
          by looking up the PDU's source address in the interface's list of
          P2MP pseudocircuits.  This includes all functions defined
          in <xref target="IS-IS">Section 7 of ISO/IEC 10589:2002</xref> and
          PDUs added in <xref target="RFC7176"/> and <xref
            target="RFC7356"/>.</t>
        <t>While possible, this document does not suggest sending such PDUs to
          multicast destinations.  All systems MUST send these PDUs to unicast
          lower layer destinations so that they are received only by the
          pseudocircuit's neighbor system.  However, systems SHOULD NOT check
          the destination address on receipt to allow future optimisations.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="LAN and P2P Hellos">
        <t>Received LAN and P2P Hello PDUs MUST be discarded when received on
          an interface configured for P2MP operation.  The system MAY notify
          the operator of such a misconfiguration.</t>
        <t>TODO: hitless migration possible?</t>
      </section>
      <section title="P2MP Hello PDUs">
        <t>P2MP Hello PDUs are divided in two categories depending on the
          presence of a RFC5303 Three-way Adjacency TLV.</t>
        <section title="Without Three-way Adjacency TLV">
          <t>For each P2MP interface that has the multicast autodiscovery
            mechanism enabled, a system periodically sends P2MP Hello PDUs
            without Three-way Adjacency TLV to a lower layer specific multicast
            address.
            The periodic timer SHOULD be configurable and is subject to jitter
            per <xref target="IS-IS">Section 10.1 of ISO/IEC 10589:2002</xref>.
          </t>
          <t>On receipt, such PDUs are not processed on any pseudocircuit's PtP 
            state machine.  They are processed on pseudocircuit management
            level as described in <!-- xref target=""/ -->:
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>If no pseudocircuit matches the PDU's lower layer source
                address, one is created for that address</t>
              <t>The pseudocircuit is held in existence at least until the
                PDU's holdtime expires.</t>
            </list>
          </t>
          <t>No information other than the neighbor's SNPA is carried from the
            PDU onto the pseudocircuit, thus most TLVs that are normally valid
            in Hellos become pointless.  However, all TLVs that affect PDU
            processing (in particular authentication TLVs) are processed
            normally.</t>
          <t>On IEEE 802 lower layers that support 48bit MAC addresses, the
            AllIntermediateSystems multicast address (09-00-2B-00-00-05) is
            used as destination when sending these PDUs.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="With Three-way Adjacency TLV">
          <t>P2MP Hello PDUs with a RFC5303 Three-way Adjacency TLV are both
            processed and generated by the PtP Hello state machine (<xref
              target="IS-IS">Section 8.2 of ISO/IEC 10589:2002</xref>) of their
            associated pseudocircuit.</t>
          <t>This implies that received PDUs are dispatched by looking up their
            source SNPA address among the pseudocircuits associated with the
            receiving interface (possibly creating a pseudocircuit).</t>
          <t>For Hello PDUs sent by the pseudocircuit's PtP Hello state
            machine, the destination SNPA address is set to the pseudocircuit's
            neighbor SNPA address.</t>
          <t>TLV validity and processing is exactly as for PtP Hellos.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="encoding" title="PDU encoding">
      <t>(Note this section follows ISO 10589 section 9, particularly in
        numbering bits starting at 1 for the LSB.)</t>
      <section title="P2MP Hello PDU">
        <figure><preamble>Figure 1: P2MP Hello PDU format</preamble>
          <artwork>
 MSB                         LSB MSB                         LSB
  8   7   6   5   4   3   2   1   8   7   6   5   4   3   2   1
+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+ - + - + - + - + - + - + - + - +
| 0x83 (Protocol Discriminator) |
+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
|       Length Indicator        |
+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
|  0x01 (Version/ID Extension)  |
+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
|           ID Length           |
+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
| R   R   R | TBD-PDU (PDU Type)|
+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
|        0x01 (Version)         |
+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
| R   R   R   R   R   R   R   R |
+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
|    Maximum Area Addresses     |
+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
| R   R   R   R   R   R |CircTyp|
+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
|           Source ID           |
:          (ID Length)          :
:                               :
+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
|                          Holding Time                         |
+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
|                           PDU Length                          |
+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
:                   Variable Length Fields (TLVs)               :
:                                                               :
</artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>All fields function exactly as for Point-to-Point IS-IS hello PDUs,
          as specified in <xref target="IS-IS">Section 9.7 of ISO/IEC
            10589:2002</xref>.</t>
        <t>Note the Local Circuit ID field is absent.  Its function is replaced
          by <xref target="RFC5303"/>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>IANA is requested to allocate a value from the "IS-IS PDU Registry" as
        follows:</t>
      <t><list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Type:">TBD-PDU</t>
          <t hangText="Description:">P2MP-HELLO-PDU</t>
          <t hangText="Reference:">This document</t>
      </list></t>
      <t>Applicability of sub-TLVs for this PDU (per "TLV Codepoints Registry")
        is per the "IIH" column.</t>
      <t>TODO: Request TBD-TLV value</t>
      <t>TODO: Request Registry TBD-TLV's Sub-TLVs</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="model" title="Configuration model">
      <t>TODO.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>TODO.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Privacy" title="Privacy Considerations">
      <t>TODO.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>TODO.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <reference anchor="IS-IS">
        <front>
          <!--   [IS-IS]    ISO/IEC 10589:2002, Second Edition, "", 2002. -->
          <title>Intermediate System to Intermediate System Intra-Domain
            Routing Exchange Protocol for use in Conjunction with the Protocol
            for Providing the Connectionless-mode Network Service (ISO
            8473)</title>
          <author>
            <organization>ISO/IEC</organization>
          </author>
          <date year="2002"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="ISO/IEC" value="10589:2002, Second Edition"/>
      </reference>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5303"?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7176"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7356"?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
<!-- vim: sw=2 ts=2 et
-->
